《新福尔摩斯》前情提要
我叫夏洛克·福尔摩斯
The name's Sherlock Holmes
地址是贝克街221B
and the address is 221B Baker Street.
午安
Afternoon.
嗯
Yeah.
他就这德行
He's always like that.
今天不太顺哈
Bad day was it?
你们昨天才成为室友
Since yesterday you've moved in with him
现在又一起查案
and now you're solving crimes together.
死了人你这么开心  真不得体
Look at you, all happy, it's not decent.
管他得不得体
Who cares about decent?
赫德森太太  游戏开始了
The game, Mrs Hudson, is on!
约翰  别搞英雄崇拜
Don't make people into heroes, John.
英雄从不存在  即使有  也不包括我
Heroes don't exist if they did, I wouldn't be one of them.
我会让你心如刀绞
I will burn the HEART out of you.
好了  这就行了
Right, this should do it.
你穿了裤子吗
You wearing any pants?
- 没有  - 好吧
- No. - OK.
我就想你记住这样的我
This is how I want you to remember me,
打败了你的女人
the woman who beat you.
但其实根本就没有什么怪物
But there never was any monster.
夏洛克
Sherlock?
终于见面了
Here we are, at last.
- 再见  约翰  - 夏洛克
- Goodbye, John. - Sherlock!
那东西会要了你的命
Those things will kill you.
你这个混蛋
Oh, you bastard!
那追逐的刺激  血脉喷张的感觉
The thrill of the chase, the blood pumping through your veins,
我们两个人一起对抗整个世界
just the two of us against the rest of the world.
等等
Wait!
我们得协调一致才行
We're going to need to coordinate.
我要你再给我一个奇迹
I asked you for one more miracle.
我求你不要死
I asked you to stop being dead.
我听到了
I heard you.
闭嘴  你根本不是解谜人
Shut up! You are not a puzzle solver, you never have been.
你只会小题大做
You're a drama queen!
现在里面有人就快死了
Now there is a man in there about to die.
游戏开始了  解开它
The game is on, solve it!
他就是勒索界的拿破仑
He is the Napoleon of blackmail.
你这次当不成英雄了  福尔摩斯先生
No chance for you to be a hero this time, Mr Holmes.
我是高智商反社会人格
I'm a high-functioning sociopath!
不论我们把夏洛克关在哪
There is no prison in which we could incarcerate Sherlock
他都会每天制造暴乱
without causing a riot on a daily basis.
而另一个办法  则需要你的获准
The alternative, however, would require your approval.
敬那些美好的时光  约翰
To the very best of times, John.
想我了吗
Did you miss me?
这怎么可能
How is this possible?
流放感觉如何
How is the exile going?
我才走了四分钟
I've only been gone four minutes.
希望你吸取教训了
Well, I certainly hope you've learnt your lesson.
这次又是谁需要我
Who needs me this time?
想我了吗
Miss me?
英国需要你
England.
在另一个世界
第二次阿富汗战争令很多人载誉而归  加官进爵
"The Second Afghan War brought honours and promotion to many.
但对我而言  那就是一场彻头彻尾的悲剧和灾难
"But, for me, it meant nothing but misfortune and disaster."
没事了  上尉
All right, Captain.
我重返英国  身体落下了终身的伤痛
"I returned to England with my health irretrievably ruined
前途一片黯淡
"and my future bleak.
鉴于此  我自然搬来了伦敦
"Under such circumstances, I naturally gravitated to London.
这里是英帝国的游手好闲者
"That great cesspool into which all the loungers..."
- 华生  - 及闲散人士的集聚之所
- Watson! - "..and idlers of the empire are drained."
华生
Watson!
我是史丹佛
Stamford.
还记得我吗
Remember?
我们以前一起在巴茨医院共事
We were at Barts together.
当然记得  史丹佛
Yes, of course. Stamford.
老天爷  你这是跑哪混去了
Good Lord! Where have you been?
搞得骨瘦如柴的
You're as thin as a rake!
我起码活着回来了  许多人还没这个福气
I made it home. Many weren't so lucky.
那现在呢
So what now?
我得找个住处落脚
I need a place to live.
条件好  价格优  这种地方可不好找
Somewhere decent at an affordable price. It's not easy.
今天还有个人和我这么说过
You know, you're the second person to say that to me today.
是谁
Who was the first?
老天爷
Good Lord.
据说是个实验
It's an experiment, apparently.
鞭笞尸体  以确立在死亡后多久
Beating corpses to establish how long after death
人体仍能形成瘀伤
bruising is still possible.
这有何医学意义吗
Is there a medical point to that?
我不确定
Not sure.
我也不确定  你所说的那位朋友呢
Neither am I. So, where's this friend of yours, then?
不好意思
Excuse me.
但愿我们没打扰到你
I do hope we're not interrupting.
你去过阿富汗吧
You've been in Afghanistan, I perceive.
华生医生  这位是夏洛克先生
Dr Watson, Mr Sherlock...
反应敏捷  你是个合适人选
Excellent reflexes, you'll do.
你说什么
I'm sorry...?
我看上了摄政公园附近的一套房子
I have my eye on a suite of rooms near Regent's Park.
我们一起应该能付得起房租
Between us we could afford them.
房子  谁说过房子的事了
Rooms? Who said anything about rooms?
我说过  我今早跟史丹佛提过
I did, I mentioned it to Stamford this morning,
我需要一位合租者
I was in need of a fellow lodger.
而午饭过后
Now he appears after lunch
他便带来了一位军人模样的男子
in the company of a man of military aspect
皮肤晒黑  最近受过伤
with a tan and a recent injury,
这两点都表明你参加了阿富汗战争
both suggestive of the campaign in Afghanistan
并被迫离开了战场
and an enforced departure from it.
所以不难得出结论了
The conclusion seemed inescapable.
我们明晚再敲定细节
We'll finalise the details tomorrow evening.
失陪了
Now, if you'll excuse me,
旺兹沃思有一场绞刑
I have a hanging in Wandsworth
我可不想错过
and I'd hate them to start without me.
- 绞刑  - 这属于我的职业范畴
- A hanging? - I take a professional interest.
我还拉小提琴  抽烟斗
I also play the violin and smoke a pipe.
这应该不成问题吧
I presume that's not a problem.
没事
Er, no, well...
你显然习惯了说话被人打断
And you're clearly acclimatized to never getting to the end of a sentence.
我们会相处得非常愉快
We'll get along splendidly.
那就约好明晚七点
Tomorrow evening, seven o'clock, then.
对了  我叫夏洛克·福尔摩斯
Oh, and the name is Sherlock Holmes
地址是贝克街221B
and the address is 221B, Baker Street.
是的  他一直都是这个样子
Yes...he's always been like that.
2015圣诞特辑
新福尔摩斯
斯特兰德月刊
卖报  卖报
Papers! Papers!
喂  《蓝宝石奇案》卖得怎么样
Here, how's The Blue Carbuncle doing?
非常受欢迎  华生医生
Very popular, Dr Watson.
下个月会有正经的谋杀案吗
Is there going to be a proper murder next month?
我会跟罪犯们谈一谈
I'll have a word with the criminal classes.
那就拜托你了
If you wouldn't mind.
那是他吗  他在车里吗
Is that him? Is he in there?
不  不不  车里不是他
No. No, no, not at all.
再见
Er, good day to you.
驾
Let on, walk.
圣诞快乐  福尔摩斯先生
Merry Christmas, Mr Holmes!
贝克街西
福尔摩斯先生
Mr Holmes!
真希望你打算回家之前能跟我打声招呼
I do wish you'd let me know when you're planning to come home!
连我自己都说不准  赫德森太太
I hardly knew myself, Mrs Hudson.
这就是乡绅分尸案的棘手之处
That's the trouble with dismembered country squires.
想提前安排日程真是难如登天
They're notoriously difficult to schedule.
- 这里面是什么  - 别管了
- What's in there? - Never mind.
谢谢
Thank you.
你抓到杀人凶手了吗  福尔摩斯先生
Did you catch the murderer, Mr Holmes?
凶手抓到了  但还在找被肢解的腿
Caught the murderer, still looking for the legs.
就算是打了个平手吧
I think we'll call it a draw.
我看到你又发表了一篇故事  华生医生
And I noticed you've published another of your stories, Dr Watson.
是的  你喜欢吗
Yes, did you enjoy it?
不喜欢
No.
- 我一直都不喜欢  - 为什么
- I never enjoy them. - Why not?
我从来连句台词都没有
Well, I never say anything, do I?
据你所写  我就只负责带人上楼
According to you, I just show people up the stairs
给你们端早餐而已
and serve you breakfasts.
在故事当中
Well, within the narrative,
这大致上就是你的职能
that is, broadly speaking, your function.
我的什么
My what?!
别觉得受了针对  赫德森太太
Don't feel singled out, Mrs Hudson,
- 写狗的那篇我都没太露脸  - 写狗的那篇
- I'm hardly in the dog one. - "The dog one?"
我是你们的房东  不是情节设置
I'm your landlady, not a plot device.
你是指《巴斯克维尔的猎犬》吗
Do you mean The Hound Of The Baskervilles?
而且你把房子写得那么沉闷昏暗
And you make the rooms so drab and dingy.
这你得怪插画家  他简直胡来
Oh, blame it on the illustrator, he's out of control!
我还得留小胡子  好让大家能认出我来
I've had to grow this moustache just so people will recognise me.
这些年来  我很荣幸能够记录
"Over the many years it has been my privilege to record
我非凡的朋友夏洛克·福尔摩斯先生的功绩
"the exploits of my remarkable friend, Mr Sherlock Holmes,
在其众多的案件中择一呈现给读者
"It has sometimes been difficult to choose which of his many cases
有时并非易事
"to set before my readers.
有些过于敏感  不便详述
"Some are still too sensitive to recount,
而有些则尚未淡出公众脑海
"whilst others are too recent in the minds of the public.
但在我们共同经历的众多冒险中
"But in all our many adventures together,
还没有哪件案子
no case pushed my friend
像《恐怖新娘》那样
to such mental and physical extremes
挑战我朋友的心理及生理极限
"as that of The Abominable Bride!"
恐怖新娘
老天爷
Good Lord!
赫德森太太  我的客厅里有个女人
Mrs Hudson, there is a woman in my sitting room!
这是故意的吗
Is it intentional?
她是客户
She's a client.
我说你出去了  她坚持要等
Said you were out, insisted on waiting.
你想坐下吗
Would you, er, care to sit down?
你有没有问她想要什么
Didn't you ask her what she wanted?
你去问她
You ask her!
你为什么不问她
Why didn't you ask her?
我怎么问  我又不说话
How could I, what with me not talking and everything?!
老天爷啊  给她点台词
For God's sake, give her some lines,
她完全可以把我们饿死
she's perfectly capable of starving us!
下午好  我是夏洛克·克福尔摩斯
Good afternoon. I am Sherlock Holmes,
这是我的朋友兼同事  华生医生
this is my friend and colleague, Dr Watson.
你可以在他面前畅所欲言
You may speak freely in front of him,
- 因为他基本听不懂  - 福尔摩斯
- as he rarely understands a word. - Holmes!
但在你开口之前
However, before you do,
容我先说说我的几点观察
allow me to make some trifling observations.
你有一种恶作剧般的幽默感
You have an impish sense of humour,
你现在就在以此
which currently you are deploying
减轻你个人的痛苦
to ease a degree of personal anguish.
你最近嫁给了一个
You have recently married a man
看起来性情温和的人
of a seemingly kindly disposition,
而他现在为一个
who has now abandoned you
品行有问题的同伴而抛弃了你
for an unsavoury companion of dubious morals.
你把来到这里当做最后的手段
You have come to this agency as a last resort,
以期你们的关系可以得到调解
in the hope that reconciliation may still be possible.
我的天啊  福尔摩斯
Good Lord, Holmes!
当然  所有这些都是从你的香水推测得来
All of this is, of course, perfectly evident from your perfume.
她的香水
Her perfume?
对  香水  让我洞悉一切  却给你带来灾难
Yes, her perfume, which brings insight to me and disaster to you.
为什么
How so?
因为我认出了它
Because I recognised it
而你没有
and you did not.
- 玛丽  - 约翰
- Mary! - John.
苍天在上  你为什么要扮成客户
Why, in God's name, are you pretending to be a client?
因为我想不出别的办法能见我丈夫  丈夫
Because I could think of no other way to see my husband, husband.
那是个国际阴谋事件
It was an affair of international intrigue.
就是个被谋杀的乡绅
It was a murdered country squire.
不管怎样  事情紧急
Nevertheless, matters were pressing.
我不介意你走  亲爱的
I don't mind you going, my darling,
- 我介意的是你扔下我  - 但你能做什么
- I mind you leaving me behind. - But what could you do?!
那你能做什么
Well, what do you do,
除了晃来晃去做笔记  时不时目瞪口呆
except wander around taking notes, looking surprised?!
够了
Enough!
舞台已经准备好  大幕升起
The stage is set, the curtain rises.
我们可以开始了
We are ready to begin.
开始什么
Begin what?
有时为了破一个案子  必须先破另一个
Sometimes to solve a case, one must first solve another.
你有案子吗  新案子
Oh, you have a case, then, a new one?
一个老案子  非常老
An old one, very old.
我必须得深入
I shall have to go deep.
深入什么
Deep? Into what?
我自己
Myself.
雷斯垂德  别在门外晃了  进来吧
Lestrade! Do stop loitering by the door and come in.
你怎么知道是我
How did you know it was me?
脚步声是不会错的
The regulation tread is unmistakable.
比琼斯轻  被格雷格森重
Lighter than Jones, heavier than Gregson.
我刚上来  哈德森太太不肯说话
I, I just came up... Mrs Hudson didn't seem to be talking.
恐怕她是在用讽刺的方法进行文学批评
I fear she has branched into literary criticism by means of satire.
这是当代房东恼人的发展趋势
It is a distressing trend in the modern landlady.
你为何事在下班时间过来
What brings you here in your off-duty hours?
- 你怎么知道我下班了  - 你到了之后
- How do you know I'm off duty? - Well, since your arrival,
超过40%的注意力都在我的酒瓶上
you've addressed over 40% of your remarks to my decanter.
华生  给探长拿点他显然想要的东西
Watson, give the Inspector what he so clearly wants.
雷斯垂德  我们能为你做什么
So...Lestrade, what can we do for you?
我不是为公事来的  我只是想过来看看
Oh, I'm not here on business, I just thought I'd drop by.
社交拜访吗
A social call?
当然  只是想给你带来节日问候
Yeah, of course, just to wish you the compliments of the season.
- 圣诞快乐  - 圣诞快乐
- Merry Christmas. - Merry Christmas.
可算客套完了
Thank God that's over.
说吧  探长  是什么奇怪的事让你来到我家
Now, Inspector, what strange happening compels you to my door,
又尴尬得说不出口
but embarrasses you to relate?
谁说出事了
Who said anything happened?
你  虽然你没有真正说出来
You did. By every means short of actual speech.
福尔摩斯  你误判了
Holmes, you have misdiagnosed.
那纠正我一下  医生
Then, correct me, Doctor.
他不是想要喝一杯  而是需要喝一杯
He didn't want a drink, he needed one.
他不是尴尬  他是害怕
He's not embarrassed, he's afraid.
我的传记作者有进步啊  成长得真快
My Boswell is learning. They do grow up so fast.
华生  给苏格兰场壮壮胆子
Watson, restore the courage of Scotland Yard.
探长  坐下吧
Inspector, do sit down.
我并不是害怕
I'm, I'm not afraid, exactly.
恐惧是面对危险时的智慧
Fear is wisdom in the face of danger,
这没什么难为情的
it is nothing to be ashamed of.
谢谢
Thank you.
从头开始讲吧
From the beginning, then.
你
You!
不要  拜托
No, please!
你
You?!
等一下
A moment.
这是什么时候的事
When was this?
昨天早上
Yesterday morning.
那个新娘的脸  是怎样描述的
The bride's face, how was it described?
"像死人一样苍白  嘴像一道绯红的伤口"
"White as death, mouth like a crimson wound."
这是编造还是事实
Poetry or truth?
很多人会说它们是一样的
Many would say they're the same thing.
对  他们都是白痴  编造还是事实
Yes, idiots. Poetry or truth?
我看到过她的脸  是在后来
I saw her face myself. Afterwards.
什么的后来
After what?
你
You?
还是我
Or me?
不是吧  雷斯垂德  一个女人当众饮弹
Oh, really, Lestrade, a woman blows her own brains out in public
你还需要我帮忙找出罪犯
and you need help identifying the guilty party?
恐怕苏格兰场又刷低了下限
I feel Scotland Yard has reached a new low.
那不是我来的原因
That's not why I'm here.
- 我猜也是  - 她叫什么名字  那个新娘
- I surmised. - What was her name, the bride?
艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂  昨天是她的结婚纪念日
Emelia Ricoletti. Yesterday was her wedding anniversary.
当然  有人报了警
The police, of course, were called.
她的尸体被送到了停尸房
And her body taken to the morgue.
这是标准程序  你为什么要告诉我们猜得到的事
Standard procedure. Why are you telling us what may be presumed?
因为接下来发生的事
Because of what happened next.
几小时之后  在莱姆豪斯
Limehouse. Just a few hours later.
托马斯·瑞克莱蒂  艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂的丈夫
Thomas Ricoletti. Emelia Ricoletti's husband.
大概是在去停尸房辨认遗体的路上吧
Presumably on his way to the morgue to identify her remains?
结果他省了这麻烦
As it turned out, he was saved the trip.
*别忘了我*
*Do not forget me*
*记住那少女*
*Remember the maid...*
你是谁
Who are you?
*磨坊的少女*
*The maid of the mill...*
你为什么要这样做  告诉我你是谁
Why are you doing this? Just tell me who you are!
你听出了我们的歌吗  亲爱的
You recognise our song, my dear?
我在婚礼上唱过
I sang it at our wedding.
艾米丽娅
Emelia?
你死了  你不可能在这里  你死了
You, you're dead, you can't be here, you died!
我美吧  托马斯
Am I not beautiful, Thomas?
跟你娶我那天一样美
As beautiful as the day you married me?
- 谁...  - 这是怎么回事
- Who... - What the hell is all this about?!
你说看起来像什么  我英俊的朋友
What does it look like, my handsome friend?
这是枪杆下的婚礼[原意:奉子成婚]
It's a shotgun wedding.
直至死亡将我们分离  他们各死了一次
Till death us do part. Twice in this case.
真离奇
Extraordinary.
不可能
Impossible.
太棒了
Superb.
当街自杀  尸体杀人
Suicide as street theatre, murder by corpse.
雷斯垂德  你简直宠坏我们了
Lestrade, you're spoiling us.
华生  拿上帽子和外套
Watson, your hat and coat.
- 我们去哪里  - 停尸房
- Where are we going? - To the morgue.
一刻也不能耽搁了
There's not a moment to lose,
很少有人会这样说停尸房
which one can so rarely say of a morgue.
那我就坐在这里吗
And am I just to sit here?
当然不了  亲爱的  我们之后会饿的
Not at all, my dear. We'll be hungry later.
福尔摩斯  有个问题  穿花呢衣服去停尸房吗
Holmes, just one thing, tweeds in a morgue?
没时间换衣服了  华生
Needs must when the devil drives, Watson.
再见  夫人
Ma'am.
我参与了一项活动
I'm part of a campaign, you know.
活动
Oh, campaign?
为女性争取投票权
Votes for women.
你是支持还是反对
And are you for or against?
出去
Get out.
他们又走了  对吧
Have they gone off again, have they?
那些先生们过着什么样的生活啊
I don't know, what a life those gentlemen lead.
是啊  那些先生们
Yes. Those gentlemen!
算了
Never you mind.
差点忘了  这是给你的
Almost forgot, that came for you.
速来
赫德森太太  告诉我丈夫我会晚归
Mrs Hudson, tell my husband I'll be home late,
我有些急事
I have some urgent business.
一切还好吧
Is everything all right?
只是有个朋友需要帮助
Oh, you know, just a, er, friend in need.
天啊  什么朋友
Oh, dear. What friend?
英格兰
England.
还真是含糊
Well, that's not very specific.
停尸房谁当班
Who's on mortuary duty?
你知道的
You know who.
总是他
Always him.
拜托告诉我这是哪个白痴干的
Please tell me which idiot did this!
这是为了大家的安全
It's for everyone's safety.
这女人死了  她半边头都不见了
This woman is dead, half her head is missing.
她对谁都不是威胁
She's not a threat to anyone.
跟她的丈夫说去吧  他在那边的罩单下
Tell that to her husband, he's under a sheet over there.
不管昨晚在莱姆豪斯发生了什么
Whatever happened in Limehouse last night,
都可以断定那不是一个死去的女人干的
I think we can safely assume it wasn't the work of a dead woman.
比这更奇怪的事都发生过
Stranger things have happened.
比如呢
Such as...?
就是...奇怪的事
Well... Strange things.
你说话跟小孩一样
You're speaking like a child.
这显然是活人干的  他去哪了
This is clearly man's work. Where is he?
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
霍普
Hooper.
你  继续工作
You, back to work!
你是来变戏法震撼我们了吧
So, come to astonish us with your magic tricks, I suppose?
你想提醒我注意什么吗
Is there anything to which you would like to draw my attention?
完全没有  福尔摩斯先生
Nothing at all, Mr Holmes.
你想什么时候走都行
You may leave any time you like.
霍普医生  是我请福尔摩斯先生来的  合作点
Dr Hooper, I asked Mr Holmes to come here. Cooperate.
这是命令
That's an order.
有两点"值得注意"
There are two "features of interest",
正如你在华生医生的故事里经常说的
as you are always saying in Dr Watson's stories.
我从没那么说过
I never say that.
你说过  很多次
You do, actually, quite a lot.
首先  这绝对是艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂
First of all, this is definitely Emelia Ricoletti.
她的身份已经确定
She has been categorically identified.
这肯定是她  毫无疑问
Beyond a doubt, it is her.
那昨晚在莱姆豪斯是谁
Then who was that in Limehouse last night?
也是艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂
That was also Emelia Ricoletti.
不可能  她死了  躺在这里
It can't have been. She was dead, she was here.
是她自己的丈夫
She was positively identified
在被杀几秒之前确认的
by her own husband, seconds before he died.
他没理由撒谎  更不可能搞错
He had no reason to lie, could hardly have been mistaken.
车夫也认识她  那就是她
The cabbie knew her, too, there's no question it's her.
但她不可能同时出现在两个地方  对吧
But she can't have been in two places at the same time, can she?
是啊  华生  对于刚死的人来说
No, Watson, one place is strictly the limit
他们只能去一个地方
for the recently deceased.
福尔摩斯
Holmes!
- 可能是双胞胎吗  - 不
- Could it have been twins? - No.
为什么
Why not?
因为从来都不是双胞胎
Because it's never twins.
艾米丽娅没有双胞胎  也没有姐妹
Emelia was not a twin, nor did she have any sisters.
她有一个哥哥  四年前去世了
She had one older brother who died four years ago.
也许是秘密的双胞胎
Hmm, maybe it was a secret twin.
什么
A what?!
秘密的双胞胎
A secret twin.
知道吗
Hmm? You know?
没人知道的双胞胎
A twin that nobody knows about.
这一切可能是策划好的
This whole thing could have been planned.
从怀孕时开始吗
Since the moment of conception.
她真是太有先见之明了
How breathtakingly prescient of her.
从来不是双胞胎  华生
It is never twins, Watson!
那你怎么看
Then what's your theory?
更重要的是  你什么毛病
More to the point, what's your problem?
- 我不明白  - 你为什么这么害怕
- I, I don't understand... - Why were you so frightened?
到目前为止  没什么能说明你为什么要喝酒
Nothing so far has justified your assault on my decanter,
还有为什么允许一个死去的女人被逮捕
and why have you allowed a dead woman to be placed under arrest?
因为还有一点"值得注意"
Ah, that would be the other feature of interest.
她指尖上有一抹血迹
A smear of blood on her finger.
血迹的由来可以有多种解释
That could have happened any number of ways.
没错
Indeed.
还有一点
There's one other thing.
之前并没有血迹
It wasn't there earlier.
那个也是新的
Neither was that.
你
You!
You?
你
You?!
福尔摩斯
Holmes?
吞枪自尽  子弹贯穿头部...
Gun in the mouth, a bullet through the brain...
后脑被轰掉
Back of the head blown clean off.
他是怎么活下来的
How could he survive?
你是说"她"吧
"She", you mean.
什么
I'm sorry?
不是"他"  是"她"
Not "He", "She".
是啊  当然了
Yes, yes of course.
谢谢你们给我这么有趣的案子
Well, thank you all for a fascinating case.
我破案之后会给你们发电报的  华生
I'll send you a telegram when I've solved it. Watson.
死因不用说是枪伤
The gunshot wound was obviously the cause of death,
但也明显有肺痨的迹象
but there are clear indicators of consumption.
还是验一下尸吧
It might be worth a postmortem.
我们需要所有能收集到的线索
We need all the information we can get.
老爸一走  他就开始显摆观察力了
Oh, isn't he observant, now that Daddy's gone
我在某些方面观察力确实很强
I am observant in some ways,
就像福尔摩斯在某些方面没有眼力见一样
just as Holmes is quite blind in others.
- 是吗  - 没错
- Really? - Yes, really.
为了在男人的天下混出头  也是蛮拼的啊
Amazing...what one has to do to get ahead in a man's world.
他这话什么意思
What's he saying that for?
干你的活儿去
Get back to work!
说吧  福尔摩斯  你肯定有些想法吧
Well, Holmes? Surely you must have some theory?
还没有
Not yet.
此案水很深  华生  很深
These are deep waters, Watson, deep waters.
但我还得继续深入
And I shall have to go deeper still.
马车夫说  "是瑞克莱蒂太太"
西区恐怖杀人案
贵族惨死
伊斯灵顿区可怕发现
小教堂惊现船长尸体
"鬼魂"身份或已确认
马车夫说  "是瑞克莱蒂太太"
下一个是谁  可怕的"新娘杀人案"
几个月后  我们才又继续
It was not for several months that we were to pick up
苏格兰场一筹莫展
汉莫斯诺子爵神秘死亡
调查这件奇案
the threads of this strange case again.
还是在出乎意料的情况之下
And then under very unexpected circumstances.
现在已经五起案子了  每起都一样
Five of them now, all the same, every one of them.
请安静  我在读至关重要的东西
Hush, please, this is a matter of supreme importance.
- 什么东西  - 黄赤交角
- What is? - The obliquity of the ecliptic.
我得读懂它
I have to understand it.
那是什么
What is it?
不知道  我还在努力弄懂它
I don't know, I'm still trying to understand it.
- 我以为你无所不知  - 当然不是了
- I thought you understood everything. - Of course not,
那多浪费我的大脑空间
that would be an appalling waste of brain space.
我是专攻型的
I specialise.
这为什么那么重要
And what's so important about this?
五起无聊的谋杀案又怎么重要了
What's so important about five boring murders?
这可不无聊  五个男人死亡
They're not boring. Five men dead,
在家中遇害  地上洒了生米
murdered in their own homes, rice on the floor
就像在婚礼上一样
like at a wedding,
墙上用血着"你"
and the word "You" written in blood on the wall!
是她  那个鬼新娘
It's, it's her, it's the Bride.
她又复活了
Somehow she's risen again.
解决了
Solved it.
你怎么就破案了
You can't have solved it!
我当然破了  非常简单
Of course I've solved it, it's perfectly simple.
神秘的瑞克莱蒂太太事件
The incident of the mysterious Mrs Ricoletti,
这位来自阴间的凶手
the killer from beyond the grave,
被媒体大肆渲染
has been widely reported in the popular press.
现在有人将自己实施的谋杀
Now people are disguising their own dull little murders
伪装成是鬼魂杀人
as the work of a ghost,
以此迷惑愚蠢至极的苏格兰场
to confuse the impossibly imbecilic Scotland Yard.
瞧  我破案了
There you are, solved.
你走前跟赫德森太太聊聊
Pay Mrs Hudson a visit on your way out,
她喜欢有参与感
she likes to feel involved.
你确定
You sure?
确定  你走吧
Certainly. Go away.
华生  我准备好了
Watson! I'm ready.
戴好帽子穿好鞋  我们有个重要约会
Your hat and boots, we have an important appointment.
华生医生几个月前不是搬走了吗
Didn't Dr Watson move out a few months ago?
确实是这样  是吧
He did, didn't he?
那我一直是在跟谁说话来着
Who have I been talking to all this time?
我代表愚蠢至极的苏格兰场说一句
Well, speaking on behalf of the impossibly imbecilic Scotland Yard,
那张椅子上没人
that chair is definitely empty.
确实没人啊
It is, isn't it?
但我这些日子过得还挺不错
Works surprisingly well, though.
我还以为他有进步了
I actually thought he was improving.
你去哪了
Where have you been?
抱歉  老爷  我今早有些迟了
Sorry, sir, I'm rather behind my time this morning.
你连蛋都不会煮吗
Are you incapable of boiling an egg?!
炉里没有火  到处是灰尘
The fires are rarely lit, there is dust everywhere
你清理我靴子上的泥时差点毁了那双鞋
and you almost destroyed my boots scraping the mud off them.
如果不是我妻子掌管佣人的事
If it wasn't my wife's business to deal with the staff,
我会亲自管教你
I would talk to you myself.
我妻子人呢
Where is my wife?
很抱歉  老爷  夫人出去了
Begging your pardon, sir, but the mistress has gone out.
这么早就出门了吗
Out? At this hour of the morning?
是  老爷  您不知道吗  老爷
Yes, sir. Did you not know that, sir?
她去哪了  她最近总出去
Where did she go? She's always out these days.
您不也是  老爷
Not unlike yourself...sir.
什么
I'm sorry...?
- 就是说说我的观察  老爷  - 够了
- Just observing, sir. - Well, that's quite enough,
谁让你观察的
nobody asked you to be observant.
抱歉  老爷  我就是说
Sorry, sir, I just meant
你们很少一起待在家里了  老爷
you're hardly ever home together any more, sir.
你的言行近乎无礼
You are dangerously close to impertinence.
我会跟我妻子谈谈  让她管教下你
I shall have a word with my wife to have a word with you.
好的  老爷  那您什么时候见她呢
Very good, sir. And when will you be seeing her?
- 听着...  - 我差点忘了  老爷
- Now, listen... - Oh, I nearly forgot, sir.
- 有封您的电报  - 你忘了
- A telegram came for you. - You forgot?!
没有  只是差点忘了
No, I nearly forgot.
你一早上都在干什么
What have you been doing all morning?
读您《斯特兰德月刊》上的新文章  老爷
Reading your new one in The Strand, sir.
你喜欢吗
Did you enjoy it?
您为什么从不提我  老爷
Why do you never mention me, sir?
下去吧
Go away.
约翰·华生医生
如方便  速来，如不方便  也速来
福尔摩斯
- 什么的什么  - 黄赤交角
- The what of the what? - The obliquity of the ecliptic.
你说"速来"  我以为是很重要的事
"Come at once," You said. I assumed it was important.
是很重要  那是地球的赤道面
It is. It's the inclination of the earth's equator
与其绕太阳运行的轨道平面的夹角
to the path of the sun on the celestial plane.
你是刚学的吧
You been swotting up?
- 我为什么要那么做  - 为了显得聪明
- Why would I do that? - To sound clever.
- 我本就聪明  - 我懂了
- I am clever. - Oh, oh, I see.
懂什么了
You see what?
我推理我们是要去见某个比你聪明的人
I deduce we're on our way to see someone cleverer than you.
闭嘴
Shut up.
第欧根尼俱乐部
保持绝对安静
早上好  怀尔德
我哥哥在吗
当然  先生
现在是早餐时间
在贵客间
是的  先生
这位先生是我的客人
是啊
是华生医生吧
很喜欢您写的《蓝宝石奇案》  先生
谢谢  很高兴你喜欢
你很  丑
您说什么
丑  你刚才说到《蓝色的鱼贩》
非常丑
很高兴你喜欢我的土豆
是的  你得多练练  华生
你在跳舞课上太下功夫了
什么
Sorry, what?
对想研究人类的人来说  这里最合适
To anyone who wishes to study mankind, this is the spot.
也很方便  毕竟你那不断扩张的屁股
Handy really, as your ever-expanding backside
永远粘在了这里
is permanently glued to it.
早上好  我的哥哥
Good morning, brother mine.
夏洛克  华生医生
Sherlock. Dr Watson.
您看上去  很不错  先生
You look...well, sir.
真的吗  我觉得我看上去很巨大
Really? I rather thought I looked enormous.
既然您提到了  这种程度的暴饮暴食
Well, now you mention it, this level of consumption
对您的健康危害极大
is incredibly injurious to your health.
- 您的心脏  - 不用担心那个  华生
- Your heart... - No need to worry on that score, Watson.
- 不吗  - 该装那个器官的地方
- No? - There's only a large cavity
只有一个大大的空腔
where that organ should reside.
- 家族通病  - 我没有指责你的意思
- It's a family trait. - Oh, I wasn't being critical.
如果您继续这样  先生
If you continue like this, sir,
我觉得您最多能活五年
I give you five years at the most.
五年  我们推测也就三年  对吧  夏洛克
Five? We thought three, did we not, Sherlock?
我还是倾向于四年
I'm still inclined to four.
你总是这样  只会看  却不懂观察
As ever, you see but you do not observe.
注意我眼白的颜色发生了变化
Note the discolouration in the whites of my eyes,
角膜周围出现可见的脂肪圈
the visible rings of fat around the corneas.
你说得对  我改赌三年
Yes, you're right. I'm changing my bet to three years,
- 四个月零十一天  - 打赌
- four months and 11 days. - A bet?!
我理解你不赞同  华生
I understand your disapproval, Watson,
但他好胜心切
but if he's feeling competitive,
完全可以控制自己早点死亡
it's perfectly within his power to die early.
这是你必须冒的险
That's a risk you'll have to take.
你在拿自己的性命打赌
You're gambling with your own life?
为什么不呢  比拿别人的命打赌有意思多了
Why not? It's so much more exciting than gambling with others'.
整三年  如果你吃了那个葡萄干布丁的话
Three years flat - if you eat that plum pudding!
就这么定了
Done.
我以为几天前会因为领主宅邸的案子见到你呢
I expected to see you a few days ago about the Manor House case.
我觉得那案子你会有点力不从心
I thought you might be a little out of your depth there.
没有  我解决了
No. I solved it.
- 肯定是亚当斯  - 是亚当斯
- It was Adams, of course. - Yes, it was Adams.
嫉妒杀人
Murderous jealousy.
他给皇家天文学会写了一篇
He'd written a paper for the Royal Astronomical Society
关于黄赤交角的论文
on the obliquity of the ecliptic,
然后又读到另一篇
and then read another
比他写的好的
that seemed to surpass it.
我知道  我读了
I know, I read it.
你看明白了吗
Did you understand it?
当然  很浅显易懂
Yes, of course I understood it, it was perfectly simple.
不是  你明白嫉妒杀人吗
No, did you understand the murderous jealousy?
一个伟大的头脑
It is no easy thing
去思忖一个更伟大的头脑可不容易
for a great mind to contemplate a still greater one.
你召我来就是为了羞辱我吗
Did you summon me here just to humiliate me?
是的
Yes.
当然不是  但这是最大的乐趣
Of course not, but it is by far the greater pleasure.
那你能不能解释下为什么要召...
Then would you mind explaining exactly why you did summon...?
我们的生活方式被一个无形敌人所威胁
Our way of life is under threat from an invisible enemy.
他们每天都常伴我们身边
One that hovers at our elbow on a daily basis.
这些敌人无处不在
These enemies are everywhere...
无人发现
undetected...
无法阻止
and unstoppable.
社会主义者吗
Socialists?
不是社会主义者  医生  不是
Not socialists, Doctor, no.
- 无政府主义者  - 不是
- Anarchists? - No.
法国人  妇女参政权论者
The French? The suffragists?
有哪个大规模团体不让你担心吗
Is there any large body of people you're not concerned about?
华生医生永远心怀警惕  详说
Dr Watson is endlessly vigilant. Elaborate...
不  去调查
No. Investigate.
这是我的推测  我需要你去证实
This is a conjecture of mine, I need you to confirm it.
我要给你个案子
I'm sending you a case.
- 苏格兰人  - 苏格兰人
- The Scots? - The Scots?!
你是否了解最近
Are you aware of recent theories concerning
关于妄想症的理论
what is known as paranoia?
听着像是塞尔维亚人
Oh, sounds Serbian.
会有位女士去找你  卡迈克夫人
A woman will call on you. Lady Carmichael.
你得接她的案子
I want you to take her case.
但这些敌人  如果你不告诉我们
But these enemies, how are we to defeat them
我们要怎么打败他们
if you won't tell us about them?
我们不会打败他们
We don't defeat them.
我们绝对要输给他们
We most certainly lose to them.
为什么
Why?
因为他们是正确的  我们是错的
Because they are right. And we are wrong.
卡迈克夫人的案子  是什么
Lady Carmichael's case, what is it?
放心  会有值得你注意的地方
Rest assured, it has features of interest.
- 我从没那么说过  - 你真说过
- I never really say that. - You really do.
我估计你已经解开了
And you've solved it already, I assume?
只是设想而已  我需要你去跑腿
Only in my head. I need you for the, er, legwork.
为什么不告诉我们你的答案
Why not just tell us your solution?
那还有什么意思呢
And where would be the sport in that?
你愿意接吗  夏洛克
Will you do it, Sherlock?
这绝对是极好的消遣
I can promise you a superior distraction.
我有一个条件  你再吃一个葡萄干布丁
On one condition. Have another plum pudding.
本来就准备吃了
There's one on the way.
两年十一个月四天
Two years, 11 months and four days.
开始好玩喽  滴答  滴答  滴答
Ha, it's getting exciting now! Ticktock, ticktock, ticktock.
谢谢  怀尔德
Thank you, Wilder.
有一位梅勒斯先生要见您  福尔摩斯先生
Also, a Mr Melas to see you, Mr Holmes.
等我五分钟  我还有一场赌局要赢呢
Give me five minutes, I have a wager to win.
还是十五分钟吧
Better make that 15.
滴答
Ticktock.
福尔摩斯先生  我是来请您出主意的
Mr Holmes, I have come here for advice.
- 这个不难  - 还要请您帮忙
- That is easily got. - And help.
这就未必容易了
Not always so easy.
有古怪的事发生了  福尔摩斯先生
Something has happened, Mr Holmes, something...unusual
而且很可怕
and...terrifying.
那您真是太走运了
Then you are in luck.
走运吗
Luck?!
那是我的专长  看来真的很有趣啊
Those are my specialisms. This is really very promising.
福尔摩斯...
Holmes...
请说说  您究竟在担忧什么
Please...do tell us what has so distressed you.
我想了很久该怎么办
I, I thought long and hard as to what to do,
后来突然想起  我丈夫
but then it occurred to me that my husband was
是您哥哥相识  也许通过他...
an acquaintance of your brother and that perhaps through him...
其实我也不确定
The fact is, I'm not sure
这事是否该找您  福尔摩斯先生
this comes within your purview, Mr Holmes.
是吗
No?
天啊  这或许是驱魔牧师的事
Lord help me, I think it may be a matter for a priest.
你的晨间危机是什么  亲爱的
And what does your morning threaten, my dear?
绣花绣得停不下来
A vigorous round of embroidering?
还是在女帽店挑花了眼
An exhausting appointment at the milliners?
你就爱说笑  尤斯塔斯
I hope you are teasing, Eustace.
怎么了
What is it?
尤斯塔斯
Eustace?
丹尼尔  索菲  出去玩会儿
Daniel, Sophie, go out and play.
妈妈...
But, Mama...
听话  快去
Look, do as I tell you, quickly now.
尤斯塔斯  这是什么意思
Well, Eustace, what does this mean?
死亡
Death.
什么
What?
这意味着死亡
It means death.
没什么  没什么
Er, nothing, it's, it's nothing.
我弄错了
I was...mistaken.
亲爱的  你的脸色怎么这么苍白
My dear, you've gone quite pale.
没事的
It's nothing!
尤斯塔斯
Eustace...
信封您还留着吗
Did you keep the envelope?
被我丈夫毁了  但上面什么也没有
My husband destroyed it, but it was blank.
没有姓名  地址  任何信息
No name or address of any kind.
尤斯塔斯爵士在美国待过吗
Tell me, has Sir Eustace spent time in America?
- 没有  - 你们结婚前也没有吗
- No. - Not even before your marriage?
据我所知没有
Well, not to my knowledge.
请您继续往下说吧
Pray, continue with your fascinating narrative.
这是上周一早上的事
Well, that incident took place last Monday morning.
两天后的周三
It was two days later on the Wednesday
我丈夫第一次看见了她
that my husband first saw her.
谁
Who?
尤斯塔斯
Eustace?
她来找我了  路易莎
She's come for me, Louisa!
天啊  帮帮我  我的罪孽找上门了
Oh, God, help me, my sins have found me out!
谁来找你了  尤斯塔斯  你吓到我了
Who's come for you? Eustace, you're frightening me.
看啊  看啊
Well, look, look!
你没看见吗
Don't you see her?
我谁也没看见
No, I see no-one.
不见了
Gone.
你对我隐瞒了那么多秘密  这又是一个吗
You keep so many secrets from me, is this another?
你看到了谁
Who have you seen?
是她
It was her!
是鬼新娘
It was the Bride!
而您什么也没看见
And you saw nothing?
是的
Nothing.
- 您丈夫描述过...  - 没有  直到今早
- Did your husband describe...? - Nothing, until this morning.
尤斯塔斯
Eustace?!
Eustace?
尤斯塔斯
Eustace?!
该死
Blast!
尤斯塔斯
Eustace?!
你在哪  是我
Where are you? It's me!
*别忘了我*
*Do not forget me*
*记住那少女*
*Remember the maid*
*磨坊的少女*
*The maid of the mill*
你是谁
Who are you?
我命令你  报上姓名
I demand you speak, who are you?!
尤斯塔斯  跟我说说话  老天啊
Eustace, speak to me. In the name of God!
她是...
She's...
她是艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂
She is Emelia Ricoletti.
不  不是你
No, not you.
不
No...
求你了
Please!
今晚  尤斯塔斯·卡迈克
This night, Eustace Carmichael,
你将必死
you will die!
- 福尔摩斯  - 别说话  华生
- Holmes? - Hush, Watson.
是艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂  鬼新娘
But Emelia Ricoletti, the Bride.
- 您知道她  - 请原谅华生
- Well, you know the name? - You must forgive Watson,
他就喜欢说出一些显而易见的事实
he has an enthusiasm for stating the obvious,
近乎狂热
which borders on mania.
容我问一句  您丈夫今早怎么样
May I ask, how is your husband this morning?
他不肯谈这件事
He refuses to speak about the matter.
当然了  我敦促他离开家
Obviously, I have urged him to leave the house.
不不  他得待在家里
No, no, he must stay exactly where he is.
您不认为他有生命危险吗
Well, you don't think he's in danger?
当然有  绝对有人想要他的命
Oh, no, somebody definitely wants to kill him,
但这对我们是好事  没有饵就钓不到鱼
but that's good for us. You can't set a trap without bait.
我丈夫可不是诱饵  福尔摩斯先生
My husband is not bait, Mr Holmes.
如果我们做对了  他就能做诱饵
No, but he could be if we play our cards right.
听着  您现在立刻回家
Now, listen, you must go home immediately.
华生医生和我会乘下一班火车跟上
Dr. Watson and I will follow on the next train.
一刻也不能耽搁了
There's not a moment to lose,
尤斯塔斯爵士今晚就要死了
Sir Eustace is to die tonight.
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
我们也许该阻止此事
And we should...probably avoid that.
- 一定要  - 一定要阻止
- Definitely. - Definitely avoid that.
我弟弟接了这案子  不出所料
Little brother has taken the case, of course.
那就拜托你留意情况了
I now rely on you to keep an eye on things,
但绝不能让他怀疑你在帮我
but he must never suspect you are working for me.
清楚了吗  华生
Are you clear on that, Watson?
你可以相信我  福尔摩斯先生
You can rely on me, Mr Holmes.
- 你说会不会...  - 不会
- You don't suppose... - No, I don't
你也不该这么想
and neither should you.
你又不知道我要说什么
You don't know what I was going to say.
你是想说  可能有什么超自然的东西
You were about to suggest there may be some supernatural agency
牵扯其中  而我打算当面嘲笑你
involved in this matter. And I was about to laugh in your face.
可那个鬼新娘  福尔摩斯
But the Bride, Holmes,
又是艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂
Emelia Ricoletti again.
一个死去的女人活过来了
A dead woman walking the earth.
- 你真让我惊讶  华生  - 是吗
- You amaze me, Watson. - I do?
你什么时候开始有想象力了
Since when have you had any kind of imagination?
或许是从我让读者相信
Perhaps since I convinced the reading public that
某个不道德的吸毒者是个绅士英雄开始
an unprincipled drug addict was some kind of gentleman hero.
是啊  说到这个  还真是了不起
Yes, now you come to mention it, that was quite impressive.
但你可以放心  这世上没有鬼
You may, however, rest assured there are no ghosts in this world.
除了我们自己想象的
Save those we make for ourselves.
抱歉  你说什么
Sorry, what did you say?
我们自己想象的鬼  什么意思
Ghosts we make for ourselves, what do you mean?
梦游症
Somnambulism.
抱歉  什么
I beg your pardon?
我会梦游  就这样
I sleepwalk, that's all.
这再常见不过了
It's a common enough condition.
你不是医生吗
I thought you were a doctor!
这整件事就是一场噩梦
The whole thing was a...bad dream.
包括你收到的信封里的东西吗
Including the contents of the envelope you received?
那是个古怪的玩笑
Well, that's a grotesque joke.
你在你妻子面前的表现可并非如此  先生
Well, that's not the impression you gave your wife, sir.
- 她有癔病  会妄想  - 不
- She's an hysteric, prone to fancies. - No.
不好意思  你说什么
I'm sorry, what did you say?
我说不  她没有癔病
I said no, she's not an hysteric.
她是个非常聪明的女人  有少见的洞察力
She's a highly intelligent woman of rare perception.
我妻子从桔核里看出了恐惧
My wife sees terror in an orange pip.
你妻子能在旁人看不见任何价值的地方
Your wife can see worlds where no-one else can see
看出很多东西
anything of value whatsoever.
真的吗
Can she really?
那你是如何"推理"出来的呢  福尔摩斯先生
And how do you "deduce" that, Mr Holmes?
她嫁给了你
She married you.
她一定是找到了什么合理的理由
I assume she was capable of finding a reason.
今晚我会尽力保护你的安全
I'll do my best to save your life tonight,
但如果你能解释一下
but first it would help
你和瑞克莱蒂一案的关系  会大有帮助
if you would explain your connection to the Ricoletti case.
瑞克莱蒂
Ricoletti?
是的  拜托具体些
Yes. In detail, please.
我从没听说过她
I've never heard of her.
有意思  我没说瑞克莱蒂是个女人
Interesting. I didn't mention she was a woman.
我们告辞了  希望明早能再见到你
We'll show ourselves out. I hope to see you again in the morning.
你不会了
You will not.
那很不幸  我就得破你的谋杀案了  日安
Then sadly I shall be solving your murder. Good day.
你尽力了
Well, you tried.
请把这个交给卡迈克夫人  谢谢
Will you see that Lady Carmichael receives this. Thank you.
- 再见  - 没问题  先生
- Good afternoon. - Certainly, sir.
那是什么
What was that?
卡迈克夫人今晚要单独睡
Lady Carmichael will sleep alone tonight,
假装头痛难忍
upon the pretence of a violent headache.
整个宅子的门窗都要紧锁
All the doors and windows of the house will be locked.
你觉得那幽灵  鬼新娘
You think the spectre, er, Bride,
会试图再次把尤斯塔斯爵士引到外面吗
will attempt to lure Sir Eustace outside again?
当然了  否则为什么放出威胁
Certainly. Why else the portentous threat?
"今晚  你将必死"
"This night you will die!"
但他不会跟她去吧
Well, he won't follow her, surely?
他会怎么做  很难说
Hmm, it's difficult to say quite what he'll do.
愧疚在吞噬他的灵魂
Guilt is eating away at his soul.
愧疚  关于什么
Guilt? About what?
他过去的某件事  那些桔核是一个提醒
Something in his past. The orange pips were a reminder.
- 不是玩笑吗  - 完全不是
- Not a joke? - Not at all.
桔核是传统的偿命预警
Orange pips are a traditional warning of avenging death,
起源于美国
originating in America.
尤斯塔斯爵士对此再了解不过了
Sir Eustace knows this only too well,
他也很清楚自己为什么要遭惩罚
just as he knows why he is to be punished.
和艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂有关吗
Something to do with Emelia Ricoletti?
我想是的
I presume.
我们都有过去  华生  有"鬼"
We all have a past, Watson. Ghosts.
那是决定我们每个晴天的阴影
They are the shadows that define our every sunny day.
尤斯塔斯爵士知道自己逃不过了
Sir Eustace knows he's a marked man.
他恐惧的不仅仅是死亡
There's something more than murder he fears.
他认为死去的瑞克莱蒂太太复活的尸体
He believes he is to be dragged to hell by the risen corpse
要把他拖进地狱
of the late Mrs Ricoletti.
这太荒谬了  不是吗
That's a lot of nonsense, isn't it?
是啊  你的左轮手枪带了吗
God, yes. Did you bring your revolver?
手枪在幽灵面前有什么用
What good would that be against a ghost?
- 对极了  你带了吗  - 当然了
- Exactly. Did you bring it? - Yeah, of course.
那就来吧  华生  来吧
Then come, Watson, come.
游戏开始了
The game is afoot.
- 蹲下  华生  真是的  - 抱歉  抽筋了
- Get down, Watson, for heaven's sake! - Sorry. Cramp.
- 灯还亮着吗  - 是的
- Is the lamp still burning? - Yes.
尤斯塔斯爵士的灯灭了
There goes Sir Eustace.
卡迈克夫人的也灭了
And Lady Carmichael.
宅子睡下了
The house sleeps.
老天  这是我这辈子最漫长的一夜了
Hmm, good God, this is the longest night of my life.
耐心点  华生
Have patience, Watson.
才到午夜
Only midnight.
我们很少这样坐在一起
You know, it's rare for us to sit together like this.
那样最好  膝盖要疼死了
I should hope so. It's murder on the knees.
两个老朋友说着话  聊着天
Two old friends just talking. Chewing the fat.
男人对男人
Man-to-man.
非凡的女人
So, a remarkable woman.
- 谁  - 卡迈克夫人
- Who? - Lady Carmichael.
女性是你的专长  华生
The fair sex is your department, Watson.
你说什么就是什么
I'll take your word for it.
你挺喜欢她的  说她"有少见的洞察力"
Well, you liked her. "A woman of rare perception."
和令人赞叹的高足弓
And admirably high arches.
她一进房间  我就注意到了
I noticed them as soon as she stepped into the room.
- 她太好了  他配不上  - 你这么认为吗
- Huh, she's far too good for him. - You think so?
不  是你这么认为  我看得出来
No. You think so. I could tell.
恰恰相反  我对此毫无看法
On the contrary, I have no view on the matter.
不  你有
Yes, you have.
婚姻不是我会思考的问题
Marriage is not a subject upon which I dwell.
- 为什么  - 你今晚是怎么回事
- Oh, why not? - What's the matter with you this evening?
你戴的那块表  里面有张照片
That watch that you're wearing, there's a photograph inside it.
我瞥过一眼  是艾琳·阿德勒吧
I glimpsed it once. I believe it is of Irene Adler.
你不只是瞥了一眼  你是等我睡着了
You didn't glimpse it, you waited till I'd fallen asleep
- 才拿去看的  - 是这样没错
- and looked at it. - Yes, I did.
- 你真以为我不会发现吗  - 艾琳·阿德勒
- You seriously thought I wouldn't notice? - Irene Adler.
一位强大的对手  一次了不起的冒险
Formidable opponent, a remarkable adventure.
- 一张漂亮的照片  - 你为什么要谈这些
- A very nice photograph. - Why are you talking like this?
你为什么坚决要孑然一身
Why are you so determined to be alone?
你没事吧  华生
Are you quite well, Watson?
这问题就这么奇怪吗
Is it such a curious question?
对于一个维也纳精神病医生来说  不奇怪
From a Viennese alienist, no.
指弗洛伊德
对于退役军医来说  当然奇怪
From a retired army surgeon, most certainly.
福尔摩斯  我是毫无竞争对手的
Holmes, against absolutely no opposition whatsoever,
- 你最亲密的朋友  - 我承认
- I am your closest friend. - I concede it.
我现在是想和你
I am currently attempting to have
谈些再正常不过的事
a perfectly normal conversation with you.
别这样
Please don't.
你为什么非要孑然一身
Why do you need to be alone?
如果你指的是感情纠葛  华生
If you are referring to romantic entanglement, Watson,
恐怕你就是  正如我以前常说的
which I rather fear you are, as I have often explained before,
我憎恶一切感情
all emotion is abhorrent to me.
感情是干扰灵敏仪器的沙粒
It is the grit in a sensitive instrument.
- 镜片上的裂纹  - 镜片上的裂纹  对
- The crack in the lens. - The crack in the lens. Yes.
这就是了
Well, there you are, you see,
- 我之前都说过  - 不  这都是我写的
- I've said it all before. - No, I wrote all that.
你在援引《斯特兰德月刊》中你自己的话
You're quoting yourself from The Strand Magazine.
就是啊
Well, exactly.
那些是我的话  不是你的
Those are my words, not yours!
那是我向公众展示的你
That is the version of you that I present to the public.
没有感情的头脑  计算机器
The brain without a heart. The calculating machine.
那些都是我写的  福尔摩斯
I write all of that, Holmes,
读者们也欣然接受  但我不相信
and the readers lap it up. But I do not believe it.
我非常想给你的编辑写信
Well, I've a good mind to write to your editor.
你是一个活生生的人
You are a living, breathing man.
- 你也有生活  也有过去  - 有什么
- You've lived a life, you have a past. - A what?!
- 你肯定有过...  - 有什么
- Well, you must have had... - Had what?
- 你懂的  - 不懂
- You know. - No.
经历
Experiences.
把左轮手枪递给我  我突然需要用一下
Pass me your revolver, I have a sudden need to use it.
见鬼  福尔摩斯  你也是血肉之躯
Damn it, Holmes, you are flesh and blood,
也有感情  你有...
you have feelings, you have...
你肯定有...冲动
You must have... impulses.
天啊  我从未如此盼望
Dear Lord, I have never been so impatient
被杀人不眨眼的鬼魂攻击
to be attacked by a murderous ghost.
作为你的朋友  作为担心你的人
As your friend, as someone who worries about you...
是什么让你变成这样的
What made you like this?
华生...
Oh, Watson...
没什么塑造了我
Nothing made me.
我塑造了自己
I made me.
红胡子
Redbeard?
我的天啊
Good God!
我们该怎么办
What are we to do?
我们去跟她聊聊吧
Why don't we have a chat?
是瑞克莱蒂太太吧
Mrs Ricoletti, I believe!
就这个时节来说  今晚真是宜人
A pleasant night for the time of year, is it not?
这不可能  福尔摩斯  不可能
It cannot be true, Holmes, it cannot!
是不可能
No, it can't.
- 锁上了  - 按照要求锁着
- Is it locked? - As per instruction.
那是打破窗户的声音  是吗
That was a window breaking, wasn't it?
我们只需要担心一扇打破的窗户
There's only one broken window we need concern ourselves with.
- 待在这儿  华生  - 什么  不
- Stay here, Watson. - What? No.
所有进出房子的门窗都锁着
All the doors and windows to the house are locked.
这是他们唯一的出口  我需要你在这儿守着
This is their only way out, I need you here!
但那声音很接近
But the sound was so close.
- 肯定是从房子这一侧传来的  - 守在这儿
- It had to be from this side of the house. - Stay here!
不
No!
你答应过保护他安全的  你答应过的
You promised to keep him safe. You promised!
你...
You...
你是人  这我知道
You're human, I know that.
你肯定是
You must be.
我们这样站在黑暗中也没什么用
Little use us standing here in the dark.
毕竟  这是十九世纪
After all, this is the 19th century.
别忘了我
Do not forget me!
- 华生  - 她在那儿  她就在那边
- Watson! - She's there! She's down there!
别告诉我你擅离职守了
Don't tell me you abandoned your post!
什么  福尔摩斯  她在那儿  我看见她了
What? Holmes, she's there, I saw her!
没人了  都怪你
Empty, thanks to you!
煮熟的鸭子飞了
Our bird is flown!
不  福尔摩斯  不是你想的那样
No! No, Holmes, it wasn't what you think.
我看见她了  那鬼魂
I saw her! The ghost!
根本没有鬼魂
There are no ghosts!
发生什么了  尤斯塔斯爵士在哪
What happened? Where is Sir Eustace?
死了
Dead.
你不能怪自己
You really mustn't blame yourself, you know.
是  你说得对
No, you're quite right.
很高兴你明白过来了
I'm glad you're seeing sense.
华生也应该受谴责
Watson is equally culpable.
我们搞砸了整个案子
Between us, we've managed to botch this whole case.
我做出承诺  要保护那个人
I gave an undertaking to protect that man,
结果他现在胸口插着匕首  倒在那里
now he's lying there with a dagger in his breast.
其实  你承诺的是调查他的谋杀案
In fact, you gave an undertaking to investigate his murder.
满怀没这个必要的自信
In the confident expectation I would not have to!
你能告诉我们什么吗  医生
Anything you can tell us, Doctor?
凶手刺杀他的力度可不小
Well, he's been stabbed with considerable force.
这么说  是男性
It's a man, then?
可能是
Possibly.
刀刃非常锋利  所以也可能是女性
A very keen blade, so it could conceivably have been a woman?
从理论上说  是的
In theory, yes,
但我们知道是谁  我看见她了
but we know who it was, I saw her.
- 华生  - 我看见鬼魂了  亲眼所见
- Watson! - I saw the ghost, with my own eyes!
你什么也没看见  你看到了别人做的戏
You saw nothing! You saw what you were supposed to see!
你自己说过的  我没有想象力
You said yourself, I have no imagination.
那就动动脑  去掉不可能的解释
Then use your brain, such as it is, to eliminate the impossible,
在这桩案子中就是鬼魂
which in this case is the ghost,
并观察余下的  那就是答案
and observe what remains, which in this case is a solution
如此明显  连雷斯垂德也能想明白
so blindingly obvious even Lestrade could work it out!
谢谢
Thank you!
别去想什么来自冥界的幽灵了
Forget spectres from the other world!
只有一个嫌疑人有作案动机和机会
There is only one suspect with motive and opportunity.
简直无异于留了字条
They might as well have left a note.
凶手确实留了字条
They did leave a note.
然后还有另一扇破窗的问题
And then there's the matter of the other broken window.
- 什么另一扇破窗  - 就是啊  根本没有
- What other broken window? - Precisely! There isn't one.
整栋房子唯一一扇破窗
The only broken window in this establishment
就是我和华生进来的那扇
is the one that Watson and I entered through,
但在那之前  我们清楚地听见了声音...
yet, prior to that, we distinctly heard the sound of...
- 你刚才说什么  - 你说什么
- What did you just say? - Sorry?
关于字条  你刚才说什么
About a note, what did you just say?
- 我说凶手确实留下了字条  - 不  没有
- I said the murderer DID leave a note. - No, they didn't.
匕首上系了张字条  你肯定看见了
There's a message tied to the dagger. You must have seen it!
- 没有什么字条  - 有的
- There's no message. - Yes!
我发现尸体的时候上面没有字条
There was no message when I found the body.
福尔摩斯
Holmes?
上面写了什么
What is it?
想我了吗
你想吗
Do you?
我想什么
Do I what?
想我了吗
你怎么拿到这个的
H-how did you get that?
我把它留在犯罪现场了
I left it at the crime scene.
犯罪现场
"Crime scene"?
你从哪学来的这些词汇
Where do you pick up these extraordinary expressions?
你想他吗
Do you miss him?
莫里亚蒂已经死了
Moriarty is dead.
但是
And yet...?
我们没找到他的尸体
His body was never recovered.
一个被推下瀑布的数学教授是该找不到
To be expected when one pushes a maths professor over a waterfall.
纯粹理性被惊险的情节推翻
Pure reason toppled by sheer melodrama.
一句话概括了你的生活
Your life in a nutshell.
你从哪学来的这些词汇
Where do you pick up these extraordinary expressions?
你又胖了吗
Have you put on weight?
你昨天才见过我  你觉得可能吗
You saw me only yesterday. Does that seem possible?
不可能
No.
但我的确又胖了
Yet here I am, increased.
全英格兰
What does that tell
最好的犯罪调查专家能从中悟到什么
the foremost criminal investigator in England?
全英格兰
In England?
你陷得很深  夏洛克
You're in deep, Sherlock,
比你预想的要深得多
deeper than you ever intended to be.
- 你列清单了吗  - 列什么
- Have you made a list? - Of what?
所有的  我们会需要张清单
Everything. We will need a list.
好样的
Good boy.
不  我还没完事
No, I haven't finished yet.
莫里亚蒂可能不敢苟同
Moriarty may beg to differ.
他想让我分心  转移我的视线
He's trying to distract me. To derail me.
没错  他是镜片上的裂纹  药膏里的苍蝇
Yes. He's the crack in the lens, the fly in the ointment,
数据里的病毒
the virus in the data.
我必须完成
I have to finish this.
如果莫里亚蒂真从莱辛巴赫的海釜里爬了出来
If Moriarty has risen from the Reichenbach cauldron,
他会找到你的
he will seek you out.
那我等着他
I'll be waiting.
是啊
Yes.
恐怕你会的
I'm very much afraid you will.
尤斯塔斯·卡迈克之死
马车夫说  "是瑞克莱蒂太太"
又一位愤怒的新娘
辉煌一生最终惨死
汉莫斯诺子爵死亡
显赫贵族惨遭袭击
苏格兰场一筹莫展
下一个是谁
他已经这样两天了
Two days he's been like that.
他吃东西了吗
Has he eaten?
没有  一口都没吃
No, not a morsel.
媒体都乐疯了
Press are having a ruddy field day.
外面还有记者蹲守
There's still reporters outside.
他们一直在那里  我赶不走他们
Oh, they've been there all the time, I can't get rid of them.
我一直忙着给他们泡茶
I've been rushed off my feet making tea.
你为什么要给他们泡茶
Why do you make them tea?
我不知道  我就那么做了
I dunno, I just sort of do.
他说"只有一个嫌疑人"  然后就走了
He said, "There's only one suspect," and then he just walks away
现在又不肯解释
and now he won't explain.
这很奇怪  他最喜欢解释了
Which is strange, because he likes that bit.
他说这案子很简单  我都能解开
Said it was so simple I could solve it.
他肯定是在夸大其词
I'm sure he was exaggerating.
你觉得他在做什么
What's he doing, do you think?
- 他说他在等待  - 等什么
- He says he's waiting. - For what?
等魔鬼
The devil.
这可难说
I wouldn't be surprised.
来这儿的什么人都有
We get all sorts here.
- 有变化的话就给我发电报  - 好的
- Well, wire me if there's any change. - Yeah.
我要说的你都想到了吧
Everything I have to say has already crossed your mind.
或许我的回答也在你脑中浮现过
Then possibly my answer has crossed yours.
像颗子弹一样
Like a bullet.
这个习惯很危险
It's a dangerous habit,
摸睡衣口袋里上了膛的手枪
to finger loaded firearms in the pocket of one's dressing gown.
还是你看到我太高兴了
Or are you just pleased to see me?
请原谅我准备了些预防措施
You'll forgive me for taking precautions.
你没准备的话我会生气的
I'd be offended if you didn't.
当然  我也礼尚往来了
Obviously, I've returned the courtesy.
我喜欢你的房间
I like your rooms.
散发着如此
They smell so...
阳刚的气息
manly.
想必你在此之前就来过了
I'm sure you acquainted yourself with them before now.
毕竟你总不在这里
Well, you are always away,
总在为《斯特兰德月刊》探险
on your little adventures for The Strand.
跟我说说  插画师和你一起出行吗
Tell me, does the illustrator travel with you?
你推理的时候  还要摆造型吗
Do you have to pose... during your deductions?
你曾六次趁我不在时来过我的公寓
I'm aware of all six occasions you have visited these apartments
- 我都发现了  - 我知道
- during my absence. - I know you are.
顺便一提  你的床意外地舒服
By the way, you have a surprisingly comfortable bed.
你知道灰尘的主要成分是人皮屑吗
Did you know that dust is largely composed of human skin?
知道
Yes.
不过味道不一样  皮肤还是新鲜的好
Doesn't taste the same, though, you want your skin fresh.
- 脆一点  - 你不坐下吗
- Just a little crispy. - Won't you sit down?
人本质上就是这样
That's all people really are, you know,
随时会飘散的灰尘
dust waiting to be distributed.
而且飘得到处都是
And it gets everywhere, didn't it?
在你呼吸的每口气里  在每束阳光里跳动
In every breath you take, dancing in every sunbeam,
那些精疲力竭的人啊
all the used-up people.
真是有趣  你坐下吧
Fascinating, I'm sure. Won't you sit...
人啊  人啊  人啊
People, people, people!
什么东西都要落灰
Can't keep anything shiny.
介意我开一枪吗
Do you mind if I fire this?
好清理下灰尘
Just to clean it out.
是啊  我们别玩了
Exactly, let's stop playing.
我们要杀彼此不需要玩具
We don't need toys to kill each other.
- 那样可不够亲密  - 坐下
- Where's the intimacy in that? - Sit down.
- 为什么  你想要什么  - 你自己要来的
- Why? What do you want? - You chose to come here.
不对  你知道不是那样的
Not true, you know that's not true.
你想要什么  夏洛克
What do you want, Sherlock?
真相
The truth.
那个啊
That.
真相很无聊
Truth's boring!
你没料想到
You didn't expect me to
我会出现在犯罪现场  是吗
turn up at the scene of the crime, did you?
可怜的尤斯塔斯爵士  他罪有应得
Poor old Sir Eustace. He got what was coming to him.
但他不可能是你杀的
But you couldn't have killed him.
那又怎样  这重要吗  够了  别这样
Oh, so what? Does it matter? Stop it. Stop this.
你才不关心尤斯塔斯爵士  还有什么鬼新娘
You don't care about Sir Eustace, or the Bride, or any of it.
整个事件中只有一样
There's only one thing in this whole business
引起了你的注意
that you find interesting.
我知道你在干什么
I know what you're doing.
新娘把枪伸进嘴里
The Bride put a gun in her mouth
把自己的后脑勺打开了花
and shot the back of her head off
然后她复活了
and then she came back.
不可能  但她做到了
Impossible. But she did it.
你想知道是怎么做到的
And you need to know how.
到底怎么回事
How?
对不对
Don't you?
因为不知道  你的世界都要崩溃了
It's tearing your world apart, not knowing.
你是想阻止我
You're trying to stop me...
想让我分心  转移我的视线
To distract me, derail me.
因为你是不是想起了另一个案子
Because doesn't this remind you of another case?
以前是不是发生过类似的事
Hasn't this all happened before?
太阳底下无新事  到底是什么
There's nothing new under the sun. What was it?
是什么呢   是哪个案子
What was it? What was that case?
你记得吗
Do you remember?
就在我嘴边  就在我嘴边
It's on the tip of my tongue. It's on the tip of my tongue.
就在我嘴边
It's on the tip of my tongue.
就在...
It's on the tip...
我嘴边
..of my tongue.
为了赫德森太太的壁纸着想  我必须提醒你
For the sake of Mrs Hudson's wallpaper, I must remind you
你的手指稍动一下  你就会死
that one false move with your finger and you will be dead.
什么
I'm sorry?
死亡
Dead...
是新的潮流
is the new sexy.
说真的  这么一来脑子还挺清爽的
Well, I'll tell you what, that rather blows the cobwebs away.
你怎么还活着
How can you be alive?
我看起来怎么样
How do I look?
老实说  是不是很显眼
You can be honest, is it noticeable?
你把脑袋打爆了  怎么可能活下来
You blew your own brains out, how could you survive?
也许我该倒梳
Or maybe I could backcomb.
我亲眼看到你死了
I saw you die.
你为什么没死呢
Why aren't you dead?
因为丧命不是因为坠落  夏洛克
Because it's not the fall that kills you, Sherlock.
你应该比别人更清楚  坠落杀不死人
Of all people, you should know that, it's not the fall,
从来都是如此
it's never the fall.
人是落地摔死的
It's the landing!
我们落地了  先生
We've landed, sir.
我们落地了
We've landed.
不不  现在不行  还不行
No, no, not now, not now!
现在不行  不行
Not now, not now.
您的旅程还舒适吧  先生
I trust you had a pleasant flight, sir?
嗯  这次流放的时间
Well, a somewhat shorter exile
没有我们想的长  弟弟
than we'd imagined, brother mine,
但考虑到你强迫症的程度  可能足够了
but probably adequate, given your levels of OCD.
- 我得回去  - 什么
- I have to go back! - What?
我就快想出来了  就差一点点
I was...I was nearly there, I nearly had it!
你到底在说什么
What on earth are you talking about?
回哪里去  你都没飞多远
Go back where? You didn't get very far.
瑞克莱蒂和他的恐怖新娘  你们不明白吗
Ricoletti and his abominable wife! Don't you understand?!
我们当然不明白  你说什么胡话呢  夏洛克
No, of course we don't, you're not making any sense, Sherlock.
是一个案子  一百年前很有名的案子
It was a case, a famous one from 100 years ago.
存在我硬盘里
Lodged in my hard drive,
她本来应该死了  但又复活了
she seemed to be dead, but then she came back.
怎么  跟莫里亚蒂一样
What, like Moriarty?
打爆了自己的脑袋  完全和莫里亚蒂一样
Shot herself in the head, exactly like Moriarty.
但你刚刚才知道
But you've only just been told.
我们也是才得知
We've only just found out,
他出现在全国每一块电视屏幕上
he's on every TV screen in the country.
是啊  怎么  麦考夫是五分钟前打的电话
Yes? So? It's been five minutes since Mycroft called.
你们有什么进展  你们做了什么
What progress have you made? What have you been doing?
更重要的是  你做了什么
More to the point, what have YOU been doing?
- 当然是进了我的思维殿堂  - 那当然
- I've been in my Mind Palace, of course. - Of course.
做思维实验  假设我在1895年
Running an experiment. How would I have solved the crime,
应该如何破案
if I'd been there in 1895?
夏洛克啊
Oh, Sherlock.
所有的细节都很清楚
I had all the details perfect.
我完全沉浸在里面  全身心的
I was there, all of it, everything. I was immersed.
当然了
Of course you were.
你在看约翰的博客  你们相遇的故事
You've been reading John's blog. The story of how you met.
有时候通过他的眼睛看我自己有好处
It helps me if I see myself through his eyes sometimes.
那样我聪明多了
I'm so much cleverer.
你真以为有人会相信你的说法
Do you really think anyone is believing you?
不  他可以做到  我见过
No, he can do this, I've seen it.
思维殿堂  他大脑中有整个世界
The Mind Palace, it's like a whole world in his head.
是的  我需要再回去
Yes, and I need to get back there.
思维殿堂是一种记忆手段  我知道它的功用
The Mind Palace is a memory technique, I know what it can do
也知道它的局限
and I know what it most certainly cannot.
也许有那么一两件事  我知道而你不知道
Maybe there are one or two things that I know that you don't.
当然有了
Oh, there are.
你列了清单吗
Did you make a list?
你又胖了
You've put on weight.
马甲显然比外套新
That waistcoat is clearly newer than the jacket.
- 别说了  你列清单了吗  - 什么清单
- Stop this! Just stop it! Did you make a list?! - Of what?
所有的  夏洛克  你服的所有药物
Everything, Sherlock. Everything you've taken.
不  不是那样  他就是出神了
No, it's not that, he goes into a sort of trance.
我见过他那样做
I've seen him do it.
从那天起  我和我弟弟达成了协议
We have an agreement, my brother and I, ever since that day.
不管在哪里找到他
Wherever I find him,
背街小巷也好  小客栈也罢
whatever back alley or doss-house...
一定要有张清单
..There will always be a list.
他不可能在五分钟内服这么多
He couldn't have taken all that in the last five minutes.
他上飞机前就嗨了
He was high before he got on the plane.
看起来不像
He didn't seem high.
瘾君子最能骗人
Nobody deceives like an addict.
我不是瘾君子  我只是服用药物
I'm not an addict, I'm a user.
减缓我的无聊
I alleviate boredom and
或者偶尔提高我的思考效率
occasionally heighten my thought processes.
老天  这可能要了你的命
For God's sake! This could kill you!
- 你可能会死的  - 控制剂量一般不会致命
- You could die! - Controlled usage is not usually fatal
节制的生活也不能永生
and abstinence is not immortality.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂  我在搜她
Emelia Ricoletti, I'm looking her up.
好吧  也许是该看看
Oh, I suppose we should.
我有权限查询军情五处的绝密资料库
I have access to the top level of the MI5 archive.
对  我正在那儿搜索
Yep, that's where I'm looking.
你认为军情五处的防火墙怎么样
What do you think of MI5 security?
弄一个也挺好的
I think it would be a good idea.
艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂  "悬案"
Emelia Ricoletti, "Unsolved",
跟他说的一样
like he says.
你们能不能闭嘴五分钟
Could you all just shut up for five minutes!
我必须回去
I have to go back.
我就快破案了
I was nearly there before
结果让你们跑进来吵没了
you stepped on and started yapping away!
吵  抱歉  我们是打扰你治疗了吗
"Yapping?" Sorry, did we interrupt your session?
夏洛克  听我说
Sherlock, listen to me.
不想听  你越说越来劲
No, it only encourages you.
- 我没生你的气  - 我真松了口气啊
- I'm not angry with you. - Oh, that's a relief!
我本来还挺担心呢  不  等等
I was really worried... No, hold on,
我真没担心
I really wasn't.
我以前救过你
I was there for you before.
下一次我还会救你
I'll be there for you again.
不论多少次我都会救你
I'll always be there for you.
这是我的错
This was my fault.
这与你无关
It was nothing to do with you.
入狱一周
A week in a prison cell,
- 我该意识到的  - 意识到什么
- I should have realised. - Realised what?
对你来说
That, in your case,
单独监禁其实是和死敌关在一起
solitary confinement is locking you up with your worst enemy.
我的神啊
Oh, for God's sake!
吗啡还是可卡因
Morphine or cocaine?
你说什么
What did you say?
我什么也没说
I didn't say anything.
不  你说了  你说
No, you did, you said...
今天是什么  吗啡还是可卡因
Which is it today? Morphine or cocaine.
福尔摩斯
'Holmes?'
吗啡还是可卡因  今天是什么
Morphine or cocaine - which is it today?
回答我  该死的
Answer me, damn it!
莫里亚蒂来过
Moriarty was here.
莫里亚蒂死了
Moriarty's dead.
我刚刚在飞机上
I was on a jet.
什么上
A what?
你也在  还有麦考夫
You were there, and Mycroft.
你就没出过门  福尔摩斯
You haven't left these rooms, Holmes.
连动都没动一下
You...haven't...moved.
告诉我  是吗啡还是可卡因
Now, tell me, morphine or cocaine?
可卡因  7%的
Cocaine. A 7% solution.
- 想来点吗  - 不想
- Would you care to try it? - No.
但我十分想把这儿所有的
But I would quite like to find every ounce of the stuff
这破玩意儿都找到然后倒窗外
in your possession and pour it out of the window.
那我会想阻止你
I should be inclined to stop you.
那我将用强有力的方式提醒你
Then you would be reminded, quite forcibly,
我们两个中谁是军人  谁是瘾君子
which of us is a soldier and which of us a drug addict.
你不是军人  你是个医生
You're not a soldier, you are a doctor.
我是个军医  所以说我可以
I'm an army doctor, which means I could
一边掰断你每一根骨头  一边叫出它的学名
break every bone in your body while naming them.
亲爱的华生  你的感情干扰了你的判断
My dear Watson, you are allowing emotion to cloud your judgment.
办案不吸毒
Never on a case.
你保证过的  办案不吸毒
You promised me, never on a case.
不  那是出自
No, I just said that
- 你的一篇故事  - 听着
- in one of your stories. - Listen,
我很乐意为你扮演捧哏
I'm happy to play the fool for you.
我可以像笨蛋一样跟着你到处跑
I will run along behind you like some halfwit,
衬托你的聪明  如果你需要的话
making you look clever, if that's what you need.
但看在上帝分上
But dear God above,
你得给自己定个更高的标准
you will hold yourself to a higher standard!
- 为什么  - 因为人们需要你那么做
- Why? - Because people need you to.
什么人  为什么  就因为你的蠢故事
What people, why? Because of your idiot stories?
没错  就因为我的蠢故事
Yes, because of my "idiot stories".
福尔摩斯先生
Mr Holmes!
福尔摩斯先生  电报  福尔摩斯先生
Mr Holmes, telegram, Mr Holmes.
怎么了  出什么事了
What is it? What's wrong?
- 是玛丽  - 玛丽  她怎么了
- It's Mary. - Mary? What about her?
- 她很有可能陷入了危险  - 危险
- It's entirely possible she's in danger. - Danger?
一刻也不能耽搁了
There's not a moment to lose.
这是你吸毒的幻觉吗
Is this the cocaine talking?
玛丽能有什么危险
What danger could Mary be in?
- 她肯定只是去拜访朋友了  - 快走
- I'm sure she's just visiting with friends. - Come on!
到底怎么了
What is happening?
你这状况真的可以吗
Are you even in a fit state?
为玛丽当然可以  这毋庸置疑  华生
For Mary, of course. Never doubt that, Watson.
毋庸置疑
Never that.
福尔摩斯
Holmes?
我没事  我没事
I'm fine. I'm fine!
别戴那顶
Not that one!
戴这顶
This one.
- 为什么  - 你是夏洛克·福尔摩斯
- Why? - You're Sherlock Holmes.
戴你该戴的帽子吧
Wear the damn hat.
马车  马车
Cab! Cab!
说吧  她在哪
So tell me, where is she?
告诉我  到底是怎么回事
You must tell me, what's going on?!
我的好华生啊
Oh, good old Watson!
你不问问题我们这些闲暇时间该怎么过啊
How would we fill the time if you didn't ask questions?!
夏洛克  快告诉我  我妻子在哪
Sherlock, tell me where my bloody wife is,
你个自大的混蛋  否则我真跟你动手
you pompous prick, or I'll punch your lights out!
福尔摩斯  她在哪
Holmes, where is she?
一间废弃教堂
A de-sanctified church.
她觉得她找到了答案
She thinks she's found the solution and,
也正因此
for no better reason than that,
她让自己陷入了巨大的危险
she's put herself in the path of considerable danger.
老婆选得真好
What an excellent choice of wife.
搞什么
What the devil?!
我找到他们了
I've found them.
这是什么啊  玛丽
What is all this, Mary?
是一切的核心  约翰
This is the heart of it all, John.
阴谋的核心
The heart of the conspiracy.
老天爷啊  这是什么地方
Great God, what is this place?
而且你为什么会在这儿
And what the devil are you doing here?!
我一直在调查
I've been making enquiries.
应福尔摩斯先生之请
Mr Holmes asked me.
福尔摩斯  你怎么能这么做
Holmes, how could you?
不  不是他  聪明的那个
No, not him, the clever one.
我认为很明显
It seemed obvious to me
这件事一个人无法完成
that this business could not be managed alone.
我认为瑞克莱蒂太太有帮手
My theory is that Mrs Ricoletti had help.
她的朋友
Help from her friends.
- 漂亮  玛丽  "聪明的那个"  - 我
- Bravo, Mary. "The clever one?" - I...
我以为我要失去你了
I thought I was losing you.
我以为我们
I thought perhaps we were...
- 在冷战  - 是你先搬出去的
- neglecting each other. - Well, you're the one who moved out.
我是在跟玛丽说话
I was talking to Mary.
你怎么为麦考夫办事了
You're working for Mycroft?
他想监督他的疯弟弟
He likes to keep an eye on his mad sibling.
而且手头正好有个间谍  你从来没发现
And he had a spy to hand. Has it never occurred to you
你妻子的能力远超普通护士吗
your wife is excessively skilled for a nurse?
他当然没发现
Of course it hasn't,
因为他了解护士的本事
because he knows what a nurse is capable of.
你又是什么时候发现的
When did it occur to you?
刚发现  不好意思
Only now, I'm afraid.
肯定很痛苦吧
Must be difficult,
当天才的笨弟弟
being the slow little brother.
也该跟上节奏了  聊够了  办正事
Time I sped up. Enough chatter, let's concentrate.
好吧  这是在干什么
Yes, all right. What's all this about?
他们想做什么
What do they want to accomplish?
进去弄个明白吧
Why don't we go and find out.
抱歉  见到锣不敲就难受
Sorry! I can never resist a gong.
- 更无法抗拒戏剧性场面  - 谁能想到呢
- Or a touch of the dramatic. - Never have guessed!
但你们好像跟我一样  喜欢戏剧性
Though it seems you share my enthusiasm in that regard.
真棒
Excellent.
一流的剧场
Superlative theatre.
场面令人赞叹
I applaud the spectacle.
艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂饮弹自尽
Emelia Ricoletti shot herself,
然后起死回生  杀死了她丈夫
then apparently returned from the grave and killed her husband.
那么...
So...
是怎么回事呢
how was it done?
整理一下这一事件吧
Let's take the events in order.
瑞克莱蒂太太用最快的速度
Mrs. Ricoletti gets everyone's attention
- 吸引了所有人的注意  - 你
- in very efficient fashion. - You!
你
You?!
还是我
Or me?
她把一把枪塞进嘴里
She places one of the revolvers in her mouth,
开火的却是枪口朝下的另一把枪
while actually firing the other into the ground.
她的同谋向窗帘上喷血
An accomplice sprays the curtains with blood
这样楼下惊慌失措的民众
and thus her apparent suicide
就都目睹了她自杀的景象
is witnessed by the frightened crowd below.
另找一具
A substitute corpse,
跟瑞克莱蒂太太非常相似的尸体
bearing a strong resemblance to Mrs. Ricoletti
来代替她  稍后被送进停尸房
takes her place and is later transported to the morgue,
这种自杀的小案子苏格兰场也没什么兴趣
a grubby little suicide of little interest to Scotland Yard.
同时真的瑞克莱蒂太太悄悄溜走
Meanwhile, the real Mrs. Ricoletti slips away.
真正聪明的是这步
Now comes the really clever part.
瑞克莱蒂太太说服一位认识她的马车夫
Mrs. Ricoletti persuaded a cab driver, someone who knew her,
拉她去丈夫最喜欢的鸦片馆外等他
to intercept her husband outside his favourite opium den.
完美的舞台  完美的一出戏
The perfect stage for a perfect drama.
你是谁  你要干什么
Who are you? What do you want?
艾米丽娅
Emelia?
救命
Help!
身份得到完全确认
A perfect positive identification.
已故的瑞克莱蒂太太起死回生
The late Mrs. Ricoletti has returned from the grave
加上精湛的化妆
and a little skilled make-up
写就了一出怨灵复仇的戏码
and you have nothing less than the wrath of a vengeful ghost.
还剩最后一件事
There was only one thing left to do.
快点  别落泪
Swiftly now. No tears.
接下来只需把真的瑞克莱蒂太太
All that remained was to substitute the real Mrs. Ricoletti
跟假尸体掉包
for the corpse in the morgue.
这次再有人来验尸
This time, should anyone attempt to identify her,
就能确认的确是她
it would be positively, absolutely her.
但她为什么要这样
But why would she do that?
用死来证明什么
Die to prove a point?
大业都需要殉道者
Every great cause has martyrs.
战争都需要献身  没错  这就是战争
Every war has suicide missions and make no mistake, this is war.
半边天向另一半宣战
One half of the human race at war with the other.
这支常伴身边的无形军队
The invisible army hovering at our elbow,
打理家事
tending to our homes,
养育孩子
raising our children.
没人注意
Ignored,
不受尊重
patronised,
被人忽略
disregarded.
投一票的权利都没有
Not allowed so much as a vote.
但依然是支军队
But an army nonetheless,
准备为崇高的事业而战
ready to rise up in the best of causes.
反抗由来已久的不平等
To put right an injustice as old as humanity itself.
所以  华生  麦考夫说对了
So you see, Watson, Mycroft was right.
这场战争我们必须输
This is a war we must lose.
她要死了
She was dying.
- 谁  - 艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂
- Who was? - Emelia Ricoletti.
能看出明显的肺痨症状
There were clear signs of consumption -
她应该是活不长了
I doubt she was long for this world.
所以她想死得有意义点
So she decided to make her death count.
她对美国的秘密社团已经很熟悉了
She was already familiar with the secret societies of America.
还使用了他们那套恐怖
And was able to draw on their methods of fear
威胁的手法  在非常公开的场合下
and intimidation to publicly, very publicly,
跟尤斯塔斯·卡迈克爵士对峙他过去的罪行
confront Sir Eustace Carmichael with the sins of his past.
他在美国结识了她
He knew her out in the States.
向她许诺了一切
Promised her everything.
婚姻  地位
Marriage, position.
然后玩弄过她...
And then he had his way with her...
就抛弃了她
..and threw her over.
丢下身无分文的她
Left her abandoned and penniless.
霍普
Hooper!
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
我得说一句  福尔摩斯  她可没瞒过我
For the record, Holmes, she didn't have me fooled.
您为什么从不提我  老爷
Why do you never mention me, sir?
艾米丽娅以为跟瑞克莱蒂会幸福
Emelia thought that she'd found happiness with Ricoletti,
但他也是个畜生
but he was a brute too.
艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂是我们的朋友
Emelia Ricoletti was our friend.
你不知道那个混账是怎么对她的
You have no idea how that bastard treated her.
可是鬼新娘  福尔摩斯  我们看到她了
But the Bride, Holmes, we saw her.
是啊  华生  看到了
Yes, Watson, we did.
打碎玻璃的声音
The sound of breaking glass?
碎的不是窗户
Not a window,
不过是个剧院的老把戏
just an old theatrical trick.
这不可能  福尔摩斯  不可能
It cannot be true, Holmes, it cannot!
是不可能
No, it can't.
叫做佩珀尔幻象
'It's called Pepper's Ghost.
一个活人
'A simple reflection in glass
新娘
在玻璃镜中的倒影
of a living, breathing person.
观众
新娘玻璃镜中的倒影
新娘
只是她们不该在搬玻璃镜时  把它弄碎
'Their only mistake was breaking the glass when they removed it.'
看看四周
Look around you.
这屋里都是新娘
This room is full of brides.
她死而复生后
Once she had risen,
就可能是任何人
anyone could be her.
尤斯塔斯·卡迈克之死
马车夫说  是瑞克莱蒂太太
复仇的鬼魂
The avenging ghost.
一个传说  令心怀不轨的男人
A legend to strike terror into the heart of any man
又一位愤怒的新娘
下一个是谁
鬼魂新娘疑云
"鬼魂"身份或已确认
马车夫说
"是瑞克莱蒂太太"
又一位愤怒的新娘
恐惧战栗
with malicious intent.
纠缠不休的鬼魂
A spectre to stalk those
与犯下罪孽却未遭惩戒的禽兽清算过去
unpunished brutes whose reckoning is long overdue.
一支愤怒军团觉醒了
A league of furies awakened.
那些我...
The women I...
我们欺骗过  背叛过的女人
WE have lied to, betrayed.
我们忽略过  蔑视过的女人
The women we have ignored and disparaged.
一旦产生了这种想法
Once the idea exists,
就难以消除了
it cannot be killed.
想出这个主意的人意志坚定
This is the work of a single-minded person.
并且亲身体会过尤斯塔斯爵士的精神虐待
Someone who knew first-hand about Sir Eustace's mental cruelty.
阴暗的秘密
The dark secret,
只告诉了她最好的朋友
kept from all but her closest friends,
包括艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂
including Emelia Ricoletti...
那个多年之前遭她丈夫亏待的女人
..the woman her husband wronged all those years before.
如果排除鬼魂
If one disregards the ghost,
就只剩一个嫌疑人
there is only one suspect.
是不是  卡迈克夫人
Isn't that right, Lady Carmichael?
但是有一个小地方我不太明白
One small detail doesn't quite make sense to me, however.
为什么要找我阻止一桩
Why engage me to prevent a murder
你打算实施的谋杀
you intended to commit?
不太明白
"Doesn't quite make sense,
doesn't quite make sense."
你当然明白不了  这不是真的
Of course it doesn't make sense, it's not real.
夏洛克啊
Oh, Sherlock.
躲躲猫
Peek-a-boo.
不
No.
不  不是你
No, not you.
不可能是你
It can't be you.
得了  闹什么呢
I mean, come on, be serious.
扮装  锣
The costumes, the gong?
作为犯罪大师
Speaking as a criminal mastermind,
我得说我们可不会用锣  或是扮装
we don't really have gongs or special outfits.
这是怎么回事
What the hell is going on?
这对你来说够蠢了吗
Is this silly enough for you yet?
够哥特了吗  够疯狂了吗  即使对你而言
Gothic enough? Mad enough, even for you?
你不明白  夏洛克
It doesn't make sense, Sherlock,
因为这不是真的
because it's not real.
- 都不是真的  - 他在说什么
- None of it. - What's he talking about?
这都是你自己在瞎想
This is all in your mind.
夏洛克
Sherlock?
福尔摩斯
Holmes!
你在做梦
You're dreaming.
他是在做梦吗
Is he dreaming?
他醒了
And there he is.
还以为你已经去了
Thought we'd lost you for a moment.
我问一下  这就是你说的"控制剂量"吗
May I just check, is this what you mean by "controlled usage"?
艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂太太  告诉我她埋在哪
Mrs Emelia Ricoletti, I need to know where she was buried.
- 你是说120年前吗  - 是的
- What, 120 years ago? - Yes.
那要找上几周才能找到  即便有这记录
That would take weeks to find, if those records even exists.
- 哪怕用我的资源来查  - 查到了
- Even with my resources. - Got it.
我不明白  和这有什么关系
I don't get it, how is this relevant?
我得先知道我是对的  然后我才能肯定
I need to know I was right, then I'll be sure.
- 你是说莫里亚蒂怎么做到的  - 没错
- You mean how Moriarty did it? - Yes.
但那些并没有发生  都是你自己想的
But none of that really happened, it was in your head.
我的调查是想象的
My investigation was the fantasy,
但犯罪方式就如我刚刚所说的那样
the crime happened exactly as I explained.
她的墓碑是她的一群朋友所立
The stone was erected by a group of her friends.
- 我不知道你以为能找到什么  - 我得试试
- I don't know what you think you'll find here. - I need to try!
艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂
挚爱的姐妹
忠诚至死不渝
艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂
挚爱的姐妹
忠诚至死不渝
艾米丽娅·瑞克莱蒂
挚爱的姐妹
忠诚至死不渝
瑞克莱蒂太太埋在这里
Mrs Ricoletti was buried here,
但是另外一具尸体呢
but what happened to the other one?
在所谓的自杀之后用来替换她的那具尸体
The corpse they substituted for her after the so-called suicide?
- 她们肯定给移走了  - 移去哪了
- They'd move it, of course they would. - But where?
不在这里
Well, not here.
但是  她们肯定会这么做
But that... that's exactly what they must have done.
同谋者有内应
The conspirators had someone on the inside.
她们找到一具尸体
They found a body,
就像茉莉·霍普给我找了具尸体
just like Molly Hooper found a body for me, when...
这不需要再说了  对吧
Yeah, well, we don't need to go into all that again, do we?
你不会真想这么做吧
You're not seriously going to do this?
我们正是为此而来  我必须知道
It's why we came here. I need to know.
真是瘾君子的口气
Spoken like an addict.
这对我来说很重要
This is important to me!
不  你这是在嗑药
No, this is you needing a fix.
- 约翰  - 莫里亚蒂回来了
- John... - Moriarty's back.
我们有案子要解决  我们有现实问题
We have a case, we have a real-life problem right now.
我下一个就解决它  就快了
Getting to that, it's next on the list.
我得先把这事做了
Just let me do this.
不  我们总是让你为所欲为
No, everyone always lets you do whatever you want.
- 所以你才落得这个样子  - 约翰  求你了
- That's how you got in this state! - John, please...
我这次不会陪你玩了  夏洛克  别想了
I'm not playing this time, Sherlock. Not any more!
你什么时候准备好工作了  给我打电话
When you're ready to go to work, give me a call.
- 我要带玛丽回家了  - 你要什么
- I'm taking Mary home. - You're what?
- 玛丽要带我回家了  - 这还差不多
- Mary's taking me home. - Better.
- 他是对的  - 对又怎么样
- He's right, you know. - So what if he's right?!
他总是对的  很无聊
He's always right, it's boring!
能帮帮我吗
Will you help me?
法国谚语
原意是如果一个男人行为怪异
就"去找到在与他偷情的女人吧"
找到这个女人吧
Cherchez la femme.
上帝啊
Oh, dear.
不在里面
The cupboard is bare.
肯定埋在下面了
They must have buried it underneath.
肯定埋在棺材下面了
They must have buried it underneath the coffin.
不走运  夏洛克
Bad luck, Sherlock.
也许她们用其他方式处理了尸体
Maybe they got rid of the body in another way.
- 不  - 很有可能
- No... - More than likely.
毕竟这是很久之前的事了
At any rate, it was a very long time ago.
而我们可还有更重要的事需要办  弟弟
We do have slightly more pressing matters to hand, little brother.
莫里亚蒂  死而复生
Moriarty? Back from the dead?
别忘了我
'Do not forget me.
'Do not forget me!'
这是
This?
我明白了
Oh, I see.
还是没醒  是吗
Still not awake, am I?
太深了  夏洛克  太深了
Too deep, Sherlock, way too deep.
恭喜  你将是史上第一个被活埋在
Congratulations, you will be the first man in history
自己的思维殿堂里的人
to be buried in his own Mind Palace.
场景布置有点夸张了  你不觉得吗
The setting is a shade melodramatic, don't you think?
对你我而言
For you and me?
一点都不夸张
Not at all.
你到底是什么
What are you?
你知道我是什么
You know what I am.
我是莫里亚蒂
I'm Moriarty.
犯罪界的拿破仑
The Napoleon of Crime.
- 莫里亚蒂已经死了  - 在你脑中可没有
- Moriarty's dead! - Not in your mind.
在你脑中我永远都不会死
I'll never be dead there.
你曾说你的大脑是块硬盘
You once called your brain a hard drive.
跟病毒打个招呼吧
Well, say hello to the virus.
这就是我们的结局  你和我
This is how we end, you and I.
总是在这里
Always here,
总是你和我一起
always together.
你的脑子很不错  莫里亚蒂
You have a magnificent brain, Moriarty.
我很敬佩
I admire it.
我认为它甚至可能与我相当
I concede it may even be the equal of my own.
我很感动
I'm touched.
我很荣幸
I'm honoured.
但说到在悬崖边缘
But when it comes to the matter of unarmed combat
徒手搏斗
on the edge of a precipice...
你等着入水吧
You're going in the water,
小矬子
short-arse.
你觉得自己高大威猛吗  夏洛克
Oh, you think you're so big and strong, Sherlock!
在我面前可不是
Not with me.
我是你的弱点
I am your weakness!
我能打倒你
I keep you down!
每次你失足  每次你失败
Every time you stumble, every time you fail,
每次你不堪一击
when you're weak,
我都
I...am...
会出现
there!
不
No,
别抵抗
don't try to fight it.
躺好  认输吧
Lie back and lose!
我们一起跳下去吧
Shall we go over together?
必须是我们一起  是吧
It has to be together, doesn't it?
到最后  永远是你
At the end it's always just you
和我
and me!
教授  麻烦你离我朋友远点
Professor, if you wouldn't mind stepping away from my friend,
我相信  他有点反感你的纠缠
I do believe he finds your attention a shade annoying.
这不公平  你们二对一
That's not fair, there's two of you!
我们总是两个人  你不看《斯特兰德月刊》吗
There's always two of us. Don't you read The Strand?
跪下  教授
On your knees, Professor.
手背到头后
Hands behind your head.
谢谢你  约翰
Thank you, John.
你什么时候开始叫我约翰了
Since when do you call me John?
你肯定想不到
You'd be surprised.
未必
No, I wouldn't.
你该醒来了  夏洛克
Time you woke up, Sherlock.
我是个讲故事的  我分得出自己是在故事里
I'm a story-teller, I know when I'm in one.
当然
Of course.
当然了  约翰
Of course you do, John.
他什么样
So what's he like?
另一个世界的我
The other me in the other place?
比看上去聪明
Smarter than he looks.
那一定很聪明了
Pretty damn smart, then.
很聪明
Pretty damn smart.
你俩直接私奔得了
Ugh, why don't you two just elope, for God's sake?!
无礼
Impertinent.
过分
Offensive.
其实  你介意吗
Actually, would you mind?
完全不
Not at all.
- 本来就该我了  - 是啊
- It was my turn. - Quite so.
你打算怎么醒过来
So how do you plan to wake up?
就这样吧
I should think like this.
你确定吗
Are you sure?
偷偷告诉你  约翰  坠落是杀不死我的
Between you and me, John, I always survive a fall.
可你是怎么做到
But how?
很简单的  亲爱的华生
Elementary, my dear Watson.
- 想我了吗  - 夏洛克  你没事吧
- Miss me? - Sherlock, are you all right?
当然没事  我怎么会有事呢
Yes. Of course I am, why wouldn't I be?
因为你可能刚服药过量  你该入院
Because you probably just OD'd. You should be in hospital.
没时间了
Hm, no time.
我得赶紧回贝克街  莫里亚蒂回来了
I have to go to Baker Street now, Moriarty's back.
我都希望他是真回来了
I almost hope he is,
如果能让你不再沉迷于此
if it'll save you from this.
现在用不着这个了
No need for that now,
我有真正好玩的了
I've got the real thing.
- 我有工作了  - 夏洛克
- I have work to do. - Sherlock...
答应我
..Promise me.
你还站这儿干什么
What are you still doing here?
你不是该去帮我搞个赦免还是什么的吗
Shouldn't you be off getting me a pardon or something,
像个好大哥那样
like a proper big brother?
华生医生
Dr Watson...
照顾好他
Look after him.
拜托
Please.
红胡子
夏洛克  等等  解释一下
Sherlock, hang on, explain.
莫里亚蒂还活着吗
Moriarty's alive, then?
我没说他活着  我说他回来了
I never said he was alive, I said he was back.
那么他死了吗
So he's dead?
他当然死了
Of course he's dead,
他开枪爆了自己的头  不可能活下来
he blew his own brains out, no-one survives that.
我刚刚为了证明这点而服药过量
I just went to the trouble of an overdose to prove it.
莫里亚蒂死了  毫无疑问
Moriarty is dead, no question.
但更重要的是  我很清楚他接下来要做什么
But more importantly, I know exactly what he's going to do next.
飞行机
Flying machines,
还有什么...电话
these, er, telephone contraptions?
这是什么疯狂的幻想啊
What sort of lunatic fantasy is that?
只是我对
It was simply my conjecture
未来世界
of what a future world might look like
和你我在其中角色的猜想
and how you and I might fit inside it.
一个逻辑学家应该可以从一滴水
From a drop of water a logician should be able to infer
推断出是大西洋还是尼亚加拉大瀑布
the possibility of an Atlantic or a Niagara.
或是莱辛巴赫瀑布
Or a Reichenbach?
- 你把这桩案子写完了吗  - 是的
- Have you written up your account of the case? - Yes.
经过修改把它写成了
Modified to put it down as
- 罕见的我未能破案的案例了吧  - 当然
- one of my rare failures, of course? - Of course.
《无形军队
The Adventure Of...
历险记》
The Invisible Army.
或者"愤怒军团"
The League Of Furies?
"恐怖军团"
The Monstrous Regiment?
我倒想起名为《恐怖新娘》
I rather thought The Abominable Bride.
- 有点庸俗  - 但会畅销的
- A trifle lurid. - It'll sell.
而且还包含了正式八经的谋杀
It's got proper murders in it too.
这方面你是专家嘛
You're the expert.
至于你的故事
As for your own tale,
你还确定你只用了7%的溶剂吗
are you sure it's still just a 7% solution that you take?
我觉得你是不是调高用量了
I think you may have increased the dosage.
或许我是有点异想天开了
Perhaps I was being a little fanciful.
但或许  这种事真的会发生
But perhaps such things could come to pass.
不管怎样  我相信我在那个世界会很自在的
In any case, I know I would be very much at home in such a world.
- 我看我不会的  - 我不敢苟同
- Huh, I don't think I would be. - I beg to differ.
但我一向知道自己是个先于时代之人
But then I've always known I was a man out of his time.